{
  "questions":[
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If the radius of the earth were to shrink by 1% its mass remaining the same, the acceleration due to gravity on the earth's surface would",
    "correct_answer": "(a)Decrease by 2%",
    "options": [
      "(a)Decrease by 2%",
      "(b)Remain unchanged",
      "(c)Increase by 2%",
      "(d)Increase by 1%"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Mass of moon is 7.34 x 10^22 kg. If the acceleration due to gravity on the moon is 1.62 m/s2, the radius of the moon is (G = 6.667 10-11 Nm2/ kg2)",
    "correct_answer": "(b)1.74 x 10^6 m",
    "options": [
      "(a)0.56 x 10^4 m",
      "(b)1.74 x 10^6 m",
      "(c)1.92 x 10^6 m",
      "(d)1.01 x 10^8 m"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Force of gravity is least at",
    "correct_answer": "(b)The poles",
    "options": [
      "(a)At the equators",
      "(b)The poles",
      "(c)A point in between equator and any pole",
      "(d)None of these"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Assuming earth to be a sphere of a uniform density, what is the value of gravitational acceleration in a 100 km below the earth's surface (Given R = 6400km).",
    "correct_answer": "(a)9.66m / s2",
    "options": [
      "(a)9.66m / s2",
      "(b)7.64m / s2",
      "(c)5.06m / s2",
      "(d)3.10m / s2"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The motion of planets around the sun is due to gravitational force of:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)Sun",
    "options": [
      "(a)Sun",
      "(b)Earth",
      "(c)Moon",
      "(d)A.O.T"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The value of the distance from the center of the earth when the gravitational acceleration has one half the value it has on the earth’s surface __________.",
    "correct_answer": "(a)1.414 Re",
    "options": [
      "(a)1.414 Re",
      "(b)2 Re",
      "(c)0.5 Re",
      "(d)Re"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "At a distance twice to the radius of the earth above the surface of earth, the value of 'g' becomes:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)1/2 g",
    "options": [
      "(a)1/2 g",
      "(b)1/4 g",
      "(c)0 g",
      "(d)"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If distance between two bodies is double and their masses are also double, the gravitational force will:",
    "correct_answer": "(c)Remains constant",
    "options": [
      "(a)Increase four times",
      "(b)Decrease four times",
      "(c)Remains constant",
      "(d)None of these"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If the distance between two masses is halved, the gravitational force is:",
    "correct_answer": "(b)Doubled",
    "options": [
      "(a)Halved",
      "(b)Doubled",
      "(c)Four times",
      "(d)Same"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If mass of earth becomes four times, the value of G is  ……… affected.",
    "correct_answer": "(d)4 times",
    "options": [
      "(a)Slightly",
      "(b)Largely",
      "(c)Lightly",
      "(d)4 times",
      "(e)Not"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Spin of the satellite affects the",
    "correct_answer": "(e)All of these",
    "options": [
      "(a)Size of satellite",
      "(b)Artificial gravity",
      "(c)Actual gravity",
      "(d)Mass of satellite",
      "(e)All of these"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The value of orbit radius of the moon is about __________.",
    "correct_answer": "(a)3.84 x 10^8 m",
    "options": [
      "(a)3.84 x 10^8 m",
      "(b)3.84 x 10^5 m",
      "(c)3.84 x 10^3 m",
      "(d)3.84 x 10^6 m"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The time taken by the moon to complete one revolution around the earth is.",
    "correct_answer": "(b)2.36 x 10^4 seconds",
    "options": [
      "(a)2.36 x 10^6 seconds",
      "(b)2.36 x 10^4 seconds",
      "(c)2.36 x 10^8 seconds",
      "(d)3.15 x 10^7 seconds"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The acceleration due to gravity decreases for a point above the surface of the earth and for the same point below the surface of the earth with a __________.",
    "correct_answer": "(b)Slow rate",
    "options": [
      "(a)Faster rate",
      "(b)Slow rate",
      "(c)Same rate",
      "(d)Constant rate"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The gravitational force of attraction between two balls each of mass 100 kg when they are placed at a distance of 1 m apart is __________.",
    "correct_answer": "(b)6.673 x 10^-11 N",
    "options": [
      "(a)6.673 x 10^-8 N",
      "(b)6.673 x 10^-11 N",
      "(c)6.673 x 10^-7 N",
      "(d)N.O.T"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The value of the gravitational acceleration at a distance equal to the earth’s radius above the earth’s surface is __________.",
    "correct_answer": "(a)9.8 m/s^2",
    "options": [
      "(a)9.8 m/s^2",
      "(b)4.9 m/s^2",
      "(c)2.45 m/s^2",
      "(d)1.09 m/s^2"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The weight of an object becomes greater in an elevator which is",
    "correct_answer": "(b)Moving up",
    "options": [
      "(a)At rest",
      "(b)Moving up",
      "(c)Moving down",
      "(d)All"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If an elevator is at rest, the apparent weight is equal to:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)ma + mg",
    "options": [
      "(a)ma + mg",
      "(b)mg - ma",
      "(c)ma",
      "(d)mg"
    ]
  },

  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The intensity of the earth's gravitational field is maximum at:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)the center of the earth",
    "options": [
      "(a)the center of the earth",
      "(b)the equator",
      "(c)the poles",
      "(d)meridian",
      "(e)any place"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Two masses 10 cm apart attract each other with a force. If these are placed 5 cm apart, what is the force as compared to the first?",
    "correct_answer": "(d)4 times",
    "options": [
      "(a)1/2 times",
      "(b)2 times",
      "(c)1/4 times",
      "(d)4 times",
      "(e)same"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Artificial gravity depends upon the ________ of satellite.",
    "correct_answer": "(e)all",
    "options": [
      "(a)size",
      "(b)axes of rotation of",
      "(c)shape",
      "(d)spin",
      "(e)all"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The satellites are put into orbit around the earth by",
    "correct_answer": "(d)rockets",
    "options": [
      "(a)aero-planes",
      "(b)missiles",
      "(c)space ship",
      "(d)rockets",
      "(e)all"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The height at which the value of gravity of earth becomes one fourth of its value on the surface of the earth is (R is earth radius):",
    "correct_answer": "(c)3R",
    "options": [
      "(a)R",
      "(b)2R",
      "(c)3R",
      "(d)4R",
      "(e)R/2"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "At 480 km above the surface of earth, gravity of earth will be ________ where earth radius 6400 km:",
    "correct_answer": "(b)7.2 m/s2",
    "options": [
      "(a)4.2 m/s2",
      "(b)7.2 m/s2",
      "(c)8.5 m/s2",
      "(d)9.63 m/s2",
      "(e)11.5 m/s2"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The atmosphere is held to the earth by",
    "correct_answer": "(b)gravity",
    "options": [
      "(a)clouds",
      "(b)gravity",
      "(c)winds",
      "(d)water",
      "(e)none"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The change in the value of ‘g’ at a height ‘h’ above the surface of the earth is the same as at a depth ‘d’ below the surface of earth. When both ‘d’ and ‘h’ are much smaller than the radius of the earth, then which one of the following is correct ?",
    "correct_answer": "(b)d = h / 2",
    "options": [
      "(a)d = 3h / 2",
      "(b)d = h / 2",
      "(c)d = h",
      "(d)d = 2h",
      "(e)h = 2d"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The source of electric energy in an artificial satellite is:",
    "correct_answer": "(d)solar cells",
    "options": [
      "(a) mini nuclear reactor",
      "(b) dynamo",
      "(c) thermopile",
      "(d) solar cell"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The value of g at a certain height above the earth is:",
    "correct_answer": "(c)estimated to decrease with altitude",
    "options": [
      "(a)nearly the same as at the surface of earth",
      "(b)nearly the same as at the center of earth",
      "(c)estimated to decrease with altitude",
      "(d)negative"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "If the space craft is 20m long, how many revolutions per minute are needed to generate artificial gravity?",
    "correct_answer": "(a)1.5",
    "options": [
      "(a)1.5",
      "(b)2.5",
      "(c)4.5",
      "(d)9.5"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Maximum effect on the weight of a body due to the rotation of the earth is at:",
    "correct_answer": "(d)equator of the earth",
    "options": [
      "(a)center of the earth",
      "(b)surface of the earth",
      "(c)poles of the earth",
      "(d)equator of the earth"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "All known planets move in:",
    "correct_answer": "(b)elliptical path",
    "options": [
      "(a)straight path",
      "(b)elliptical path",
      "(c)circular path",
      "(d)hyperbolic path"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A body is taken from the earth’s surface to the moon, the weight of the body will be zero at a point where force of attraction due to the",
    "correct_answer": "(c)moon is zero",
    "options": [
      "(a)earth is zero",
      "(b)moon and earth is equal and opposite",
      "(c)moon is zero",
      "(d)both the moon and earth is zero"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "An object is taken from the earth to a planet where the value ‘g’ is 20 m/s^2. If it is compared with the value of ‘g’ on earth, which of the following statements is true?",
    "correct_answer": "(a)weight on the planet will be greater",
    "options": [
      "(a)weight on the planet will be greater",
      "(b)weight on the planet will be the same",
      "(c)mass on the planet will be greater",
      "(d)mass on the planet will be smaller"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A boy standing in a lift falling freely under gravity releases a ball from his hand. As seen by him, the ball",
    "correct_answer": "(b)remains stationary",
    "options": [
      "(a)falls down",
      "(b)remains stationary",
      "(c)goes up",
      "(d)goes forward"
      
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Which force in nature exists everywhere?",
    "correct_answer": "(d)gravitational force",
    "options": [
      "(a)nuclear force",
      "(b)electromagnetic force",
      "(c)electrical force",
      "(d)gravitational force"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Two planets have the same average density but their radii are R1 and R2. If acceleration due to gravity on these planets be g1 and g2 respectively, then...",
    "correct_answer": "(b)g1/g2 = R2/R1",
    "options": [
      "(a)g1/g2 = R1/R2",
      "(b)g1/g2 = R2/R1",
      "(c)g1/g2 = R1^2/R2^2",
      "(d)g1 x g2 = R1 x R2"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The acceleration of the moon is approximately equal to:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)earth gravity",
    "options": [
      "(a)earth gravity",
      "(b)earth gravity",
      "(c)earth gravity",
      "(d)earth gravity"
    ]
  },

  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Which one of the following planets is closer to the sun?",
    "correct_answer": "(d)mercury",
    "options": [
      "(a)pluto",
      "(b)mars",
      "(c)venus",
      "(d)mercury"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The planet nearest to the earth is:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)venus",
    "options": [
      "(a)venus",
      "(b)mercury",
      "(c)sun",
      "(d)moon"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "Pull of the earth on a mass of 20 kg on the surface of earth is:",
    "correct_answer": "(b)196N",
    "options": [
      "(a)20N",
      "(b)196N",
      "(c)19.6N",
      "(d)1960N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The weight of a man in an elevator moving down with acceleration of 9.8 m/s^2 will become.",
    "correct_answer": "(d)double",
    "options": [
      "(a)half",
      "(b)zero",
      "(c)unchanged",
      "(d)double"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A man of mass 100 kg is standing in an elevator. The net force on the man when the elevator is going up with an acceleration of 4 m/s^2 would be:",
    "correct_answer": "(d)1380N",
    "options": [
      "(a)908N",
      "(b)490N",
      "(c)100N",
      "(d)1380N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A body of 2 kg is suspended from the ceiling of an elevator moving up with an acceleration 'g'. Its apparent weight in the elevator will be:",
    "correct_answer": "(c)129.4N",
    "options": [
      "(a)9.8N",
      "(b)19.6N",
      "(c)129.4N",
      "(d)39.2N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The expression for the orbital velocity of the satellite in terms of orbit radius is:",
    "correct_answer": "(d)",
    "options": [
      "(a)",
      "(b)",
      "(c)",
      "(d)"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A man weighs 980 N in a stationary lift. What will be the weight if the lift starts moving up with an acceleration of 4.9 m/s^2?",
    "correct_answer": "(a)1960N",
    "options": [
      "(a)1960N",
      "(b)980N",
      "(c)1176N",
      "(d)1470N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "The law of gravitation was introduced by:",
    "correct_answer": "(c)Newton",
    "options": [
      "(a)Huygen",
      "(b)Boyle's",
      "(c)Newton",
      "(d)Pascal"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A body of mass 2 kg is suspended in an elevator by means of a spring balance. The balance reads its weight when the elevator moves up with an acceleration of 5 m/s^2 as:",
    "correct_answer": "(b)29.6N",
    "options": [
      "(a)30.5N",
      "(b)29.6N",
      "(c)26.5N",
      "(d)9.8N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A body of mass 1 kg is suspended in an elevator by means of a spring balance. The balance reads its weight when the elevator moves down with an acceleration of 4 m/s^2 as:",
    "correct_answer": "(c)13.8N",
    "options": [
      "(a)9.8N",
      "(b)5.8N",
      "(c)13.8N",
      "(d)20N"
    ]
  },
  {
    "category": "Physics",
    "type": "multiple",
    "difficulty": "medium",
    "question": "A body in a satellite orbiting round the earth is weightless because:",
    "correct_answer": "(a)no net force acts on it",
    "options": [
      "(a)no net force acts on it",
      "(b)the moon attracts the body with a force equal to its weight",
      "(c)it is far away from the earth to experience pull of the earth",
      "(d)the force applied by the moon on the body is equal to the force applied by the earth on the body"
    ]
  }
]
}